Guide to the Robert Schwartz Papers TAM.392
Tamiment Library and Robert F. Wagner Labor Archives
Robert Schwartz Papers
1936-2000
1960-1989
Tamiment Library and Robert F. Wagner Labor Archives
Schwartz, Robert J., 1917-2006
TAM.392
16.50 Linear Feet in 15 record cartons, 2 manuscript boxes, 1 half manuscript box, and 3 oversize folders in shared housing.
4.8 Megabytes
Robert J. Schwartz was a American-born economist and stock-broker. He was an early advocate of socially responsible investing (SRI). He also actively campaigned for civil rights, against the Vietnam War, and against the use of nuclear weapons. He actively participated in many organizations such as Americans for Democratic Action (ADA), SANE/FREEZE (later known as Peace Action), Advocates for Children, Trust for Balanced Investment, and Social Investment Forum (SIF). He founded Economists Against the Arms Race/Economists Allied for Arms Reduction (ECAAR), later called Economists for Peace and Security (EPS), which sought to document the economic costs of military activities. Some of his disarmament activism brought him on U.S. deleations to the Soviet Union, China, and South Korea in the late 1980s. In 1966, he ran unsuccessfully on an antiwar platform for the Democratic nomination for the seat in New York's 17th Congressional district. This collection documents Robert Schwartz's work and activist from his time as a student to his work post-retirement. The collection is organized primarily by the organizations in which Robert Schwartz served. The materials represented in these groupings include meeting minutes, agendas, annual reports, correspondence and memos, notes, newsletters, and research materials. Additionally, these groupings may also include drafts of speeches, articles, reports, proposals, and other manuscripts and notes. In addition to Robert Schwartz's activism materials, the collection contains correspondence relating to his political, activist, professional, and personal lives. In addition to letters, the correspondence files include materials such as greeting cards, newspaper clippings, invitations, mailers and promotional materials, shared manuscript drafts and edits, etc. The collection also contains his college and graduate work, materials from his time working in the Treasury Department and as a Marine during World War II.
Conditions Governing Access
Materials are open without restrictions with the exception of confidential health records in box 18.
Immediate Source of Acquisition
There is no documentation about the provenance of this collection. The accession number associated with this collection is 1950.007.
Arrangement
This collection has not been arranged by an archivist. The materials are arranged in the order in which they were received from the donor.
Physical Characteristics and Technical Requirements
Born-digital materials have not been transferred and may not be available to researchers. Researchers may request access copies. To request that material be transferred, or if you are unsure if material has been transferred, please contact tamiment.wagner@nyu.edu with the collection name, collection number, and a description of the item(s) requested. A staff member will respond to you with further information.
Biographical Note
Robert J. Schwartz (1917-2006) was a American-born economist and stock-broker. He was an early advocate of socially responsible investing (SRI). He also actively campaigned for civil rights, against the Vietnam War, and against the use of nuclear weapons. He actively participated in many organizations such as Americans for Democratic Action (ADA), SANE/FREEZE (later known as Peace Action), Advocates for Children, Trust for Balanced Investment, and Social Investment Forum (SIF). He founded Economists Against the Arms Race/Economists Allied for Arms Reduction (ECAAR), later called Economists for Peace and Security (EPS), which sought to document the economic costs of military activities. Some of his disarmament activism brought him on U.S. deleations to the Soviet Union, China, and South Korea in the late 1980s. In 1966, he ran unsuccessfully on an antiwar platform for the Democratic nomination for the seat in New York's 17th Congressional district.
Scope and Contents
This collection documents Robert Schwartz's work and activist from his time as a student to his work post-retirement. The collection is organized primarily by the organizations in which Robert Schwartz served. The materials represented in these groupings include meeting minutes, agendas, annual reports, correspondence and memos, notes, newsletters, and research materials. Additionally, these groupings may also include drafts of speeches, articles, reports, proposals, and other manuscripts and notes. In addition to Robert Schwartz's activism materials, the collection contains correspondence relating to his political, activist, professional, and personal lives. In addition to letters, the correspondence files include materials such as greeting cards, newspaper clippings, invitations, mailers and promotional materials, shared manuscript drafts and edits, etc. The collection also contains his college and graduate work, materials from his time working in the Treasury Department and as a Marine during World War II.
Economists -- Political activity -- United States.; Stockbrokers; Investments -- Moral and ethical aspects; Nuclear disarmament.; Peace Action (Organization); SANE/FREEZE: Campaign for Global Security; Advocates for Children (New York, N.Y.); Economists Allied for Arms Reduction (Organization); Americans for Democratic Action; Social Investment Forum (U.S.); Economists Against the Arms Race (Organization)
- Correspondence, Advocates for Children, Council on Economic Priorities, Save the Earth Trust, 1971-1994 (Box 1)
- Save the Earth Trust, Interracial Council for Business Opportunity, Correspondence, 1962-1990 (Box 2)
- Correspondence, 1983-1990 (Box 3)
- Correspondence, Socially Responsible Investing (SRI), 1970-1989 (Box 4)
- Interfaith Center on Corporate Responsibility, Correspondence, Blue Diamond, SRI, 1943-1988 (Box 5)
- SRI, SANE/FREEZE, Americans for Democratic Action, 1964-1990 (Box 6)
- SANE/FREEZE, Vietnam, Americans for Democratic Action, 1957-1980 (Box 7)
- SANE/FREEZE, Congressional Run, 1965-1969, 1984-1990 (Box 8)
- SANE/FREEZE, 1960-1994 (Box 9)
- Correspondence, Social Investment Forum (SIF), South Korea and USSR Delegations, Treasury/Interior Materials, 1941-1999 (Box 10)
- SRI, Correspondence, SANE/FREEZE, China, 1970-1994, 2000 (Box 11)
- Jo Schwartz Correspondence, SANE/FREEZE, Congressional Run, 1938-1941, 1962-1999 (Box 12)
- Trust for Balanced Investment, SRI, SANE/FREEZE, 1938, 1969, 1973-1996 (Box 13)
- Trust for Balanced Investment, Council for Economic Priorities, Interracial Council for Business Opportunity, Economists Against the Arms Race (ECAAR), SIF, 1942-1991 (Box 14)
- Correspondence, Employment and Academic Work, Israel Discount Bank (IDB), Americans for Democratic Work, 1936-1968 (Box 15)
- SANE/FREEZE, Photographs, 1961-1983 (Box 16)
- SANE, ECAAR, 1959-1972, 1992, 2000 (Box 17)
- Awards/Emblems (Box Shared Tamiment 054, Folder 7)
- First NY Daily Press and Other Newspaper Clippings (Box Shared Tamiment 054, Folder 8)
- New York Times Magazine Article (Box Shared Tamiment 062, Folder 19)